<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Mohamed Kamal</title>
    <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Mohamed Kamal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture: A 4-Dimensional View</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/head-first-architecture-dimensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/head-first-architecture-dimensions/</guid>
      <description>Software Architecture: A 4-Dimensional View Link to heading Note: I took these note while reading &amp;ldquo;Head First Software Architecture: A Learner&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Architectural Thinking by Mark Andrew Richards, Neal Ford, and Raju Gandhi&amp;rdquo;. I also used AI to clean it.&#xA;Software architecture isn&amp;rsquo;t a singular concept, but rather a multi-dimensional approach to building robust and adaptable systems. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore these key dimensions:&#xA;1. Architectural Characteristics&#xA;Architectural characteristics are the essential capabilities your system needs to possess.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Quorums Ensure Agreement in Distributed Systems</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/majority-quorum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/majority-quorum/</guid>
      <description>In distributed systems, where tasks are spread across multiple interconnected machines, quorums provide a fundamental mechanism for ensuring data consistency and system-wide agreement. In essence, a quorum is a minimum number of nodes (machines) that must agree on an operation for it to be valid. Think of it like a voting threshold. An update to a database or the election of a leader in a cluster – these actions only happen if a designated group (the quorum) participates and reaches a consensus.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharding: A Coffee Shop Analogy</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/sharding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/sharding/</guid>
      <description>Remember our last blog post where we tamed the rush of order requests with a team of baristas dedicated to just reading orders? Well, get ready for another challenge! Our beloved coffee shop is brewing with excitement thanks to new customers and delicious new drinks. This means a flood of updates and sign-ups, and our trusty &amp;ldquo;master barista&amp;rdquo; who handles all these changes is feeling the pressure.&#xA;Just like throwing more baristas at a long line wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be the smartest idea, we need a well-thought-out plan to tackle this avalanche of updates.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replication Topologies for Scaling: A Coffee Shop Analogy</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/replication-toplogies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/replication-toplogies/</guid>
      <description>Following the coffe shop analogy in the previous blog post, the coffee shop is booming, and you need to expand your team to handle the growing customer base. But simply adding more baristas isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. You need a well-organized system to ensure smooth operations, quick recovery from unexpected situations, and efficient storage of customer preferences. This is where replication topologies come in – different ways to structure your team of baristas and order pads (replicas) to achieve specific goals.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replication and Sharding: A Coffee Shop Analogy</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/replication-and-sharding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/replication-and-sharding/</guid>
      <description>Setting the Stage for Distributed Storage Link to heading Non-distributed Storage (Single-Master System):&#xA;Imagine your favorite local coffee shop. Keeping track of customer preferences on a simple notepad (single-server database) is a breeze. New entries are readily added, and the system is clear-cut. However, as the shop&amp;rsquo;s popularity explodes, the notepad becomes a bottleneck.&#xA;Read Replication Link to heading Read Replication:&#xA;The coffee shop thrives and attracts more customers. To handle the increased workload, the barista team expands.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kafka Fundamentals: APIs, Topics and Partitions</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/kafka-fundamentals-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/kafka-fundamentals-part1/</guid>
      <description>Kafka is an event streaming platform designed to handle massive volumes of real-time data efficiently. At its core lies a distributed storage system built for scalability, ensuring it can seamlessly accommodate ever-growing data demands.&#xA;This distributed nature allows Kafka to function as a cluster of machines, each playing a role in storing the data stream. This approach offers significant advantages:&#xA;Scalability: As data volumes increase, additional nodes can be added to the cluster, effectively distributing the storage burden and ensuring smooth operation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microkernel Architecture (Plug-in Architecture)</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microkernel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microkernel/</guid>
      <description>Microkernel architecture is an architecural style where a minimal core system (the microkernel) handles generic or stable domain tasks. Other functionalities are provided by pluggable modules and communicate with the core system through well-defined interfaces.&#xA;You might encounter it in familiar applications:&#xA;Web Browser Extensions: Many web browsers allow you to install extensions that add new functionality. These extensions act as plug-ins, extending the core features of the browser without modifying its core code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Layered Architecture Style</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/layered-architecture-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/layered-architecture-style/</guid>
      <description>The layered architecture is a monolithic architectural style that organizes an application into horizontal layers, each focused on distinct technical concerns.&#xA;Understanding the Terms:&#xA;Monolithic application: The entire application is deployed as a single unit. Distributed application: Application components are split across different machines and communicate through a network. Technical partitioning: Application components are organized based on technical aspects like data access or user interface, rather than business domains. Layers in the Layered Architecture:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> Microservices: An Extreme Form of Decoupling for Large-Scale Systems</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microservices-and-coupling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microservices-and-coupling/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Link to heading The microservices architecture style represents an extreme form of decoupling tailored for large-scale systems where hundreds of developers collaborate simultaneously. By embracing logical, spatial, temporal, and technology decoupling, teams can work autonomously and iterate rapidly. In this post, we delve into how microservices reduce coupling at various levels, enabling scalability, agility, and independent deployability.&#xA;Microservices: Decoupling at Scale Link to heading Microservices architecture represents a paradigm shift in software development, embodying the principles of extreme decoupling to address the challenges of building and maintaining large-scale applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> Microservices:  Communication Styles</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microservices-synchronus-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/microservices-synchronus-communication/</guid>
      <description>A communication style refers to the way microservices interact with each other to exchange information and complete tasks. There are two main communication styles:&#xA;Synchronous communication Asynchronous communication Synchronus Communication Link to heading In microservices architecture, synchronous communication is a method for services to interact with each other directly. It follows a request-response pattern, where one service sends a request to another and waits for a response before continuing. This is similar to how traditional client-server applications work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding XSS Attacks and Contextual Encoding in Go</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/xss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/xss/</guid>
      <description>XSS (Cross-Site Scripting) Link to heading XSS is a critical security vulnerability that arises when a web application allows an attacker to inject malicious scripts into web pages, which are then viewed by other users. Contextual encoding serves as a crucial defense mechanism against XSS attacks. When user input is presented on a web page, it must undergo proper encoding to ensure that any potential script content is treated as data rather than executable code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go Context Package: Cause-aware Context Cancellation</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/cause/</guid>
      <description>The context package in Go has recently introduced cause-aware context cancellation functions. This update includes the WithCancelCause, WithDeadlineCause, and WithTimeoutCause functions, as well as the Cause function for retrieving the cause of context cancellation.&#xA;func WithCancelCause(parent Context) (ctx Context, cancel CancelCauseFunc) This function is analogous to WithCancel, but it returns a CancelCauseFunc that allows setting an error as the cause of cancellation.&#xA;func WithDeadlineCause(parent Context, d time.Time, cause error) (Context, CancelFunc) Combining features of WithDeadline with the ability to provide a cause for context cancellation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go Context Package: AfterFunc</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/afterfunc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/afterfunc/</guid>
      <description>The AfterFunc function in Go&amp;rsquo;s context package provides a robust tool for scheduling the execution of a specified function after a given context concludes, be it due to cancellation or a timeout. This blog post delves into the practical application of AfterFunc through an illustrative example, shedding light on its functionality and potential use cases.&#xA;The AfterFunc Signature Link to heading func AfterFunc(ctx Context, f func()) (stop func() bool) ctx: The context that determines when the function f should be executed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Workflow: Deploying Node.js Apps with Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/k8s-pods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/k8s-pods/</guid>
      <description>Prerequisites Link to heading To successfully follow and execute the App Deployment Workflow within a Kubernetes environment, you&amp;rsquo;ll need the following prerequisites:&#xA;Software and Tools Link to heading Node.js: Ensure Node.js is installed on your local development machine to set up and manage the Node.js application.&#xA;Docker: Docker is essential for containerizing your application into a Docker image. Make sure Docker is installed and configured correctly to build and manage containerized applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplify Configuration Management in Go with the &#39;conf&#39; Package</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/go-conf-pkg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/go-conf-pkg/</guid>
      <description>The &amp;ldquo;conf&amp;rdquo; package is designed to make configuration management in Go straightforward and flexible. It allows you to define your application&amp;rsquo;s configuration as a struct and then parse it for both environment variables and command-line arguments. This approach makes it easy to handle different configuration sources, and the package provides a variety of customization options through struct tags.&#xA;First, you need to install the &amp;ldquo;conf&amp;rdquo; package:&#xA;go get github.com/ardanlabs/conf/v3 Define a struct that represents your application&amp;rsquo;s configuration.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Go&#39;s init Functions: Best Practices and Common Misuses</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/go-init-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/go-init-functions/</guid>
      <description>In Go, init functions play a crucial role in package initialization. They are used to set up the initial state of your application, and their behavior can be both powerful and tricky to manage. In this blog post, we&amp;rsquo;ll delve into the concept of init functions, their use cases, execution order, and common pitfalls.&#xA;What Are init Functions? Link to heading In Go, an init function is a special type of function used for package-level initialization.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Essential Docker Commands</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/docker-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/docker-commands/</guid>
      <description>Display Docker Version Information Link to heading docker version This command provides information about the Docker Engine version.&#xA;List All Docker Images Link to heading docker images This command lists all the Docker images available on your system.&#xA;Pull an Image from the Registry Link to heading docker pull &amp;lt;image_name&amp;gt; You can use this command to download a Docker image from a container registry, like Docker Hub.&#xA;Create and Run a New Ubuntu Container with Interactive Shell Link to heading docker run -it &amp;lt;image&amp;gt; /bin/bash This command starts a new Docker container based on the specified image and opens an interactive shell (in this case, /bin/bash) inside the container.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Docker for Go</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/docker-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/docker-go/</guid>
      <description>What Is a Container? Link to heading Containers are like isolating an application so it thinks it&amp;rsquo;s running all by itself. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to a virtual machine (VM) but uses the host&amp;rsquo;s operating system instead of its own. To start a container, you begin with a container image that bundles up everything the application needs to run, making it easy to share and distribute.&#xA;The isolation that tricks a container into believing it has control over a whole Linux machine is achieved through the use of namespaces and control groups.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
