<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Microservices on Mohamed Kamal</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/microservices/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Microservices on Mohamed Kamal</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/microservices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data Sharing Between Microservices Using Synchronized Embedded Caches</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/caching_data-shraing-embedded-cache/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/caching_data-shraing-embedded-cache/</guid>
      <description>Setting the Scene Link to heading Consider an online food delivery system with two essential microservices:&#xA;Menu Service: Manages the list of available dishes. Order Service: Allows customers to create and manage their orders. How It Works Link to heading Starting the Menu Service:&#xA;The menu service starts and loads a cache containing information about available dishes. This cache is distributed, enabling it to be shared across different services. Starting the Order Service:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> Microservices:  Communication Styles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/microservices-synchronus-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/microservices-synchronus-communication/</guid>
      <description>A communication style refers to the way microservices interact with each other to exchange information and complete tasks. There are two main communication styles:&#xA;Synchronous communication Asynchronous communication Synchronus Communication Link to heading In microservices architecture, synchronous communication is a method for services to interact with each other directly. It follows a request-response pattern, where one service sends a request to another and waits for a response before continuing. This is similar to how traditional client-server applications work.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
