<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mohamed Kamal</title>
    <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/authors/mohamed-kamal/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mohamed Kamal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/authors/mohamed-kamal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding XSS Attacks and Contextual Encoding in Go</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/xss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/xss/</guid>
      <description>XSS (Cross-Site Scripting) Link to heading XSS is a critical security vulnerability that arises when a web application allows an attacker to inject malicious scripts into web pages, which are then viewed by other users. Contextual encoding serves as a crucial defense mechanism against XSS attacks. When user input is presented on a web page, it must undergo proper encoding to ensure that any potential script content is treated as data rather than executable code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go Context Package: Cause-aware Context Cancellation</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/cause/</guid>
      <description>The context package in Go has recently introduced cause-aware context cancellation functions. This update includes the WithCancelCause, WithDeadlineCause, and WithTimeoutCause functions, as well as the Cause function for retrieving the cause of context cancellation.&#xA;func WithCancelCause(parent Context) (ctx Context, cancel CancelCauseFunc) This function is analogous to WithCancel, but it returns a CancelCauseFunc that allows setting an error as the cause of cancellation.&#xA;func WithDeadlineCause(parent Context, d time.Time, cause error) (Context, CancelFunc) Combining features of WithDeadline with the ability to provide a cause for context cancellation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go Context Package: AfterFunc</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/afterfunc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/afterfunc/</guid>
      <description>The AfterFunc function in Go&amp;rsquo;s context package provides a robust tool for scheduling the execution of a specified function after a given context concludes, be it due to cancellation or a timeout. This blog post delves into the practical application of AfterFunc through an illustrative example, shedding light on its functionality and potential use cases.&#xA;The AfterFunc Signature Link to heading func AfterFunc(ctx Context, f func()) (stop func() bool) ctx: The context that determines when the function f should be executed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Workflow: Deploying Node.js Apps with Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/k8s-pods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkabdelrahman.github.io/posts/k8s-pods/</guid>
      <description>Prerequisites Link to heading To successfully follow and execute the App Deployment Workflow within a Kubernetes environment, you&amp;rsquo;ll need the following prerequisites:&#xA;Software and Tools Link to heading Node.js: Ensure Node.js is installed on your local development machine to set up and manage the Node.js application.&#xA;Docker: Docker is essential for containerizing your application into a Docker image. Make sure Docker is installed and configured correctly to build and manage containerized applications.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
